Finding Aid for the Eugene Newton Anderson Papers, 1924-1978 LSC.2074
UCLA Library Special Collections
Eugene Newton Anderson papers
1924-1978
UCLA Library Special Collections
Anderson, Eugene Newton
LSC.2074
2 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Eugene Newton Anderson (1900- ) was a professor of history at the University of Nebraska where he was attacked during the McCarthy period by the American Legion for the use of a certain textbook. He later joined the UCLA Department of History. His publications include The first Moroccan crisis, 1904-06 (1930) and Nationalism and the cultural crisis in Prussia, 1806-15 (1939). The collection consists of Anderson's personal and professional correspondence, manuscripts and publications, and the American Legion allegations made against him in the 1950s.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Eugene N. Anderson, 1978.
Gift of Mrs. E.N. Anderson, 1985.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 994621913606533
Biography
Anderson was born July 24, 1900 in Texas; BA, Chemistry, University of Colorado, 1921; Ph.D, European history, University of Chicago, 1928; studied at University of Berlin, 1924-25, and returned to Germany on Social Sciences research fellowship, 1930-31; published The first Moroccan crisis, 1904-06 (1930) and Nationalism and the cultural crisis in Prussia, 1806-15 (1939); became Associate Chief of the Division of Occupied Areas, U.S. Department of State, 1945; taught at University of Chicago before World War II; taught at University of Nebraska and attacked during McCarthy period for use of textbook; came to UCLA; associated with various modern artists.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of personal and professional correspondence and manuscripts of UCLA professor of history Eugene Anderson. Letters describe travels in Germany and also give details of European and California artists. Correspondents include Rainer Maria Rilke, Ernst Barlach, John McLaughlin, and Rufino Tamayo. Includes manuscripts and publications by Anderson and American Legion allegations during the McCarthy period while Anderson taught at University of Nebraska.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Family letters sent from Germany (Box 1).
Personal and professional correspondence and papers (Boxes 1-3).
Letters from artists and writers (Boxes 3-4).
Manuscripts and publications (Box 4).
Historians -- United States -- Archives.; Art, Modern -- 20th century.; Artists -- 20th century -- Correspondence.; Anderson, Eugene Newton--Archives.; University of California, Los Angeles--Faculty -- Archives
- Family Letters; Sent from Germany
  - Letters from Trip to Germany, 1924-25.; Holograph, addressed to Mither
    - 1924, July-December., 56 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      From: New York City, aboard Sierra Ventana, Berlin, and Bremen.
    - 1925, January-September., 77 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      From: Berlin, Budweis, Paris, Rouen, and Mont St. Michel.
  - Letters from Trip to Germany, 1930-31.; Holograph, addressed to Mither, to J.M., and Ross.
    - 1930, June-December., 146 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      From: Chicago, New York City, Plymouth, Devon, Cornwall, London, Berlin, and Geneva.
    - 1931, January-July., 119 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      From: Berlin.
      Includes 8 pieces from Pauline Relyea, later Anderson; and one newspaper clipping.
    - 1931, July-September., 98 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      From: Berlin, Florence, Rome, and Naples.
      Includes 10 pieces from Pauline.
  - Trip to Germany, 1937
    - Account of sojourn in Germany -, summer 1937.; 35 leaves. Typescript. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Written in the form of a letter to Dear Mother. Ste. Anne d'Auray, Brittany, August 30, 1937.
  - Education Mission Group to Germany, 1946
    - Photographs., 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters from Trip to Germany, 1949.; Holograph and typed.
    Addressed to family with various familiar names
    - 1949, May-August., 61 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      From: Washington, D.C., Frankfurt, Bad Nauheim, Wiesbaden, Bonn, Muenster, Bremen, Göttingen, Heidelberg, Freiburg, Hamburg, and Munich.
    - Photographic postcards, 1949, v.d.; 10 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      From: Lindau, Bad Nauheim, Innsbruck, Heidelberg, Stuttgart, Oberammergau, Bad Godenburg, Hamburg, Schloss Neuschwaustein, and Vienna.
    - Photograph. Frei universitat, Berlin, 1949.; 1 piece. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters from Trip to Germany, 1958; (Holograph, addressed to Pauline)
    - 1958: June-July., 73 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      From: Bonn, Nüremberg, Frankfurt, Hamburg, Berlin, and Marburg.
      Also: 2 newspaper clippings.
    - Photographic postcards, 1958, v.d.; 6 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      From: Fulda, Göttingen, Marburg/Lahn, Köln, and Berlin.
    - Photographs, 1958.; 19 items. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Personal and Professional Correspondence and Papers
    - 1930-39., 80 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Harley Farmsworth MacNair and Florence Wheelock Ayscough, Later MacNair
    - From Harley MacNair, 1930-35 and n.d.; 44 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - From Florence Ayscough, 1930.; 5 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Photograph of HFM and FWA, 7 September 1935.; 1 piece. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Printed announcement of the marriage of HFM and FWA, 1935.; 1 piece. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - James Westfall. Thompson Festschrift Volume - ENA and James L. Cate (co-editors); Frances E. Gillespie (co-editor?)
    - Letters to Miss Gillespie, 1931 and 1934.; 6 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Letters to ENA from JLC, 1936-37 and n.d. (presumably 1937).; 16 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Letters to ENA from contributors or those solicited for contributions, 1933-37.; 35 pieces. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1939-42., 8 pieces (1939) and 56 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes letter from James Westfall Thompson. One letter is addressed to Pauline Anderson.
  - Ernst Posner
    - Letters from Posner and Mrs. Posner., 1939, 1944, 1954, 1956, 1958-70, 1972-73, 1975-77.; 36 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Enclosure. Newspaper clipping, June 1961. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Enclosure. Photographs., 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Letter from Ken Munden, October 1966.; 1 piece. (Box 2, Folder 5)
      About Posner festschrift.
  - Sub-Committee on Studies of National Socialist Germany, American Committee for International Studies, 1940
    - Letters from William W. Lockwood, American Committee for International Studies, Princeton, to ENA., July, September-0ctober and December 1940.; 28 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Letters from other committee members to ENA, July-October and December 1940.; 28 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Copies of letters to Lockwood, sent to ENA., July-October 1940.; 13 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Copies of ENA's letters, September 1940.; 6 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Materials from Edward Mead Earle, July-August 1940 and n.d.; 9 pieces. Includes: The American Committee for International Studies [a description of the committee and its aims] [1]6 leaves. n.d. Typescript (mimeograph). (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - ENA's holograph notes, n.d.; 15 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Memoranda by ENA, August-September 1940.; 11 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Ideas for projects and studies by the committee; from various members, August 1940 and n.d.; 33 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Organizational materials. Agendas, etc., August 1940 and n.d.; 13 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Reports. A proposal for studies of National Socialist Germany; report of the Sub-Committee on Studies of National Socialist Germany to the American Committee for International Studies, November 1940.; [12] leaves. Typescript (mimeograph). Plans for the study of National Socialism and totalitarianism drawn up by the War seminar at the University of Michigan for the consideration of the American Committee for International Studies. Ann Arbor, January 1941, 21 leaves. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1942, 1945, and 1947-50., 81 pieces. Includes letter from Herbert Marcuse. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1950-54., 48 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - American Legion Allegations, 1952
    - Letters received, December 1952-February 1953.; 31 pieces. Includes letter from Owen Lattimore. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Letters received, n.d.; 10 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Letters received, with enclosures, December 1952.; 8 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - ENA's holograph notes., 9 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Newspaper articles by or using material by ENA, March 1950, March and December 1952.; Clippings, 4 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Clippings about Lattimore, March 1950.; 2 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Clippings about allegations against ENA., December 1952, January and March 1953.; 54 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 1954-56., 16 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - 1959-64, 1966-72 and n.d., 63 pieces (dated) and 10 pieces (n.d.). (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - History Institute, Peshawar University, Pakistan, 1961
    - ENA's letters to Pauline; one postcard from Hong Kong, June-August 1961.; 163 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Pauline's letters to ENA, July-August 1961 and n.d.; 21 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Letters of appreciation from students, 1961-66 and n.d.; 39 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Enclosures. Photographs, unidentified., 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Roster, letter from ENA (report on experiences in Pakistan, with recommendations, etc.) and ENA's Report to the Asis Foundation on my experience with the History Institute, Peshawar University, Peshawar, Pakistan during, June and July 1961.; 21 pieces. (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Also letters of appreciation written to ENA by the staff of the Asia Foundation.
  - Letters from Former Students of ENA
    - From Dave Hettig, 1966-69.; 13 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - From Sheldon and Anne Thorne, 1968-73 and n.d.; 38 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - From Charles, 1970.; 2 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      With the above three folders: 1 leaf holograph note by ENA explaining keeping these letters.
    - From William and Marjorie Sywak, 1970-72.; 20 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Former students (1 leaf holograph note by ENA) residing in Chile.
    - From Donald and Shari Rosenberg, 1976-78 and n.d.; 66 pieces and 1 leaf holograph note by ENA. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1972-78., 24 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - From Hans and Helene Rosenberg, 1974-78.; 8 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Also 1 leaf holograph note by ENA, explaining the return of HHR letters.
  - Letters from Artists and Writers, Arranged in Alphabetical Order by Sender
    - Miscellaneous, A - Z. (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Includes one letter from the following: Laura Andresen, Lee Burket, Martha Davidson, Richard Dunlap, Lukas Foss, Norman A. Geske, Lex Haas, Jascha Kessler, Florence McLaughlin (wife of artist John Mclaughlin), Esther Robles, Lawrence Urrutiz, Karl With, and Susan Wyngaard.
    - Andrews, Dorothy., 1977 and n.d.; 3 pieces correspondence, 2 pieces enclosure and 8 pieces manuscript. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Brown, William Theo and Paul Wonner
    - From Brown, 1969-70, 1972-77.; 54 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - From Brown, n.d.; 28 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - From Brown. Postcards, n.d.; 8 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - From Wonner, 1972-74, 1976.; 11 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - From Wonner. Postcards, 1969, 1971, 1973.; 3 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - From Wonner, n.d.; 28 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - From Wonner. Postcards, n.d.; 9 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - From Brown and Wonner. Postcards, 2 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Announcements of Brown and Wonner shows at Felix Landau Gallery, 2 pieces. Newspaper clipping, review of show of work by Wonner. 1972. 1 piece. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Color snapshot of Bill Brown and Paul Wonner, 1 piece. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Burckhardt, Hans and Thordis
    - 1974 and n.d., 3 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1976 and n.d.; 2 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Cremean, Robert
    - 1972-77., 62 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - n.d., 8 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Announcements, 1974 and 1977.; 3 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Review. Newspaper clipping, 1973.; 1 piece. (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Margaret Cremean (the artist's mother) to ENA; Robert de la Vergne to ENA, about Cremean's work., 1974 and 1975.; 2 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Harden, Marvin
    - 1975-76., 3 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Announcement, 1976.; 1 piece. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Jones, John Paul
    - 1965, 1967-70, 1973-74., 10 pieces and 1 undated piece. (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Newspaper clipping, 1973.; 1 piece. (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Mallory, Margaret., 1973 and n.d.; 4 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Marcks, Gerhard
    - 1958, 1960, 1962-65, 1967-69, 1971-73, 1975-76, 1978., 47 pieces. Includes 1 blank leaves. and 1 leaf holograph from Mrs. Marcks. (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - n.d., possibly 1974., 1 piece. (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Enclosures to letters from Marcks. Newspaper clippings, 1973-74.; 2 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Letter about Marcks, 1962.; 1 piece. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - ENA on Marcks. Holograph note; letter to Pauline,; and journal of Marcks's visit to ENA, June 1958 October 1963.; 1 leaf; 4 leaves; and 16 leaves. (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Heigs, Pete., 1957 and n.d.; 2 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Mills, Margaret., 1975-77.; 5 pieces. Also: Mills, Wallace. 1975. 1 piece. (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Nullican, Lee
    - 1969-76., 30 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - n.d., 1 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Nullican, Luchita., 1970.; 3 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Petrunak, Karl., 1976-77 and n.d.; 5 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Possatti, Rudy., 1955, 1957, 1959-60, 1962-63, 1970-71, 1974 and n.d.; 23 pieces. (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Shipp, Eve., 1976 and n.d.; 7 pieces. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Wankaner, Jitendvasiulu of
    - 1972-73, 1975-76., 11 pieces. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - ENA's letter of recommendation for the Wankaners, [?]., 1976; 3 pieces. Reply, 1976. 1 piece. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Whiteside, Forbes., 1954 and 1959.; 8 pieces. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Wildenhain, Marguerite
    - 1968-1977., 48 pieces. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Photocopy of letter, E. Naurice Bloch to Dorothy Millon, 1974.; 1 piece. Newspaper clipping about Gerhard Marcks, 1969. 1 piece. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Wonner, Paul, (folders 10-18, Box 3)
    General note
    See: Brown, William Theo and Paul Wonner
- Manuscripts and Publications by Eugene N. Anderson
  - Student and Early Writings - Dealing Primarily with Germany
    - President Hindenburg, 1920.; 19 leaves. Carbon typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Mariolatry in the Middle Ages. Written as a grad student., [25] leaves. Holograph. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - An interpretation of the Reformation, 1922.; 14 [leaves]. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Quarterly reports, SSAC. [Untitled], 1930. (Box 4, Folder 10)
      1st quarterly report. 3 leaves. Holograph.
      [2nd] 1931. 3 leaves. Holograph.
      [3rd, 1931] 4 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections.
      [4th? 1931] 9 leaves. Carbon typescript.
    - The unpolitical Germans. Berlin, 1930.; 11 leaves. Typescript with minor holograph corrections. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - [Untitled], 1951.; 11 leaves. Holograph. (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Speech read before abt. 40 or 50 German students, writers, & officials at a private home in Berlin - ab. Feb. 1931.
    - The danger in Germany. Chicago, 1933.; 7 leaves. Typescript. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - The domestic aspects of nationalism, with special reference to Germany., 24 leaves. Typescript with minor holograph corrections. (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Also: 2 leaves holograph notes, evidently someone's criticisms.
    - Die Wirtung der Reden Fichtes. Offprint from Forschungenzurbrandenburgischen und preussischen Geschichte, vol.50 (), pp.65-87., 1927 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Reviews
    - Untitled. Review of: The international anarchy, 1904-1914; by Goldsworthy Lowes Dickinson. New York and London, 1926. (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Clipping from: International journal of ethics, April 1927, pp.317-321.
    - The drifting grey. Review of: British foreign policy under Sir Edward Grey. [New York, ]., 19 September 1928 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Clipping from: The nation, vol.127 no.3298, pp.274-75.
    - Germany's past. Review of: History of Germany; by Hermann Pinnow. New York, 26 August 1933. (Box 4, Folder 18)
      Clipping from: The Saturday review of literature.
    - Untitled. Review of: The individual and his society; by Abram Kardiner. New York, 1939. (Box 4, Folder 19)
      Offprint from: Psychiatry reviews. n.d. pp.443-45.
  - Papers
    - [Untitled] beginning: The economic and social history of Germany in the nineteenth century.... Read at AHA meeting, n.d. 1931.; 15 leaves. Typescript. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Liberalism and nationalism in western Europe, Read at AHA meeting., 20 leaves. (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Time in history. Los Angeles[?] [?]. ... as given at Mt. St. Mary's College in.. .1967., 32 leaves. Typescript. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Later Writings - History
    - Imperialism and industrial society. ca., 1952.; 23 leaves. Carbon typescript. (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Imperialism and modern war. ca., 1952.; 30 leaves. (Box 4, Folder 24)
      With this: holograph letter from John Galbraith, n.d. 1 leaf.
    - The engineers' stake in international affairs, n.d.; 11 leaves. Typescript (mimeograph). (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Social humanities - a proposal. [?]., 1966; 8 leaves. Carbon typescript. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - The Writing of Social History, 1969
    - The writing of social history. Santa Barbara, 1969.; [4] p. leaves. 19 [1] 69 leaves. Incomplete. (Box 4, Folder 27)
      Consists of two chapters listed in the table of contents: Social history; and The training of a social historian. Typescript and holograph, with note (1978) by ENA: I tried to publish a volume containing these essays - in vain. I gave some of the essays to former students and only by chance did I keep a few.
    - Social history, with holograph note: chapter I., n.d.; 17 leaves. Typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 4, Folder 28)
      Also: 2 holograph leaves. inserted between leaves 1 and 2. Copy above incorporates these corrections.
    - Social time in history., 31 leaves. Typescript with minor holograph corrections. (Box 4, Folder 29)
      Has note: revised Feb 73.
    - The aesthetic approach to historical study., 42 leaves. Carbon typescript with minor holograph corrections. (Box 4, Folder 30)
      Has note: 1968?
    - Elements of cultural style., 43 leaves. Typescript with extensive holograph corrections and additions. (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Art, Artists, etc.
    - Ernst Barlach., 1954.; 61 leaves. Typescript with extensive holograph additions and corrections. (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Conversation with Tamayo., 1964.; 8 leaves. Typescript. (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Letter to Ceeje Gallery about Marvin Harden., 1966.; 1 leaf. (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - The landscape, 10 [8] leaves. Holograph. (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Translation of Rilke on landscape., 8 leaves. Holograph. (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - [Conway Pierson pottery exhibit], n.d.; Typescript with extensive holograph corrections. (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Post-death and the arts. Santa Barbara, November 1977.; 2pp. Holograph. (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - From Christian art to cosmic art. Santa Barbara, 1978.; 9 leaves. Holograph. (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Cosmic art. Santa Barbara, 1978.; 12 leaves. Carbon typescript. (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Publications
    - Process vs. power. Letters received, primarily in response to complimentary copies., April-July 1952, January and June 1953.; 25 pieces. (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Untitled review [in a Scandinavian language] of Political institutions and social change in continental Europe in the nineteenth century; by Eugene N. Anderson and Pauline R. Anderson. Berkeley and Los Angeles, 1967.; Clipping (photocopy). 2 leaves. (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Works of Reflection, Philosophy, etc.
    - A personal statement. Santa Barbara, June 1977.; 3pp. Holograph. (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Language of the soul., September 1977.; 7pp. [on 5 leaves]. (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Thought and fantasy in old age. Santa Barbara, November 1977.; 7 leaves. Typescript with extensive holograph corrections. (Box 4, Folder 45)
      Present holograph title replaces typed title: Old age and the life of the hermit.
    - [Untitled] beginning: We shall soon be celebrating birthdays, and on these occasions I wonder once more about the nature of time., 1 leaf. Holograph. (Box 4, Folder 46)
      Also: 1 leaf typescript copy.